Guide to the United Women Firefighters Records WAG.057
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series III: Organizational Files, 1977-2002; 6 Linear Feet in 6 record cartons; 24 videocassettes; 5 videodiscs (dvd)
  This series consists of organizational files of the United Women Firefighters (UFW) from 1977-2002, and of Women in Fire Service (WFS), alternately known as Women in Fire Suppression, from 1983-1995.
  This series is divided into two subseries by creating organization.
  - Subseries A: United Women Firefighters, 1977-2002
    This subseries includes materials related to the founding and operation of the UWF, such as clippings, correspondence, organizational materials, press conferences, the FDNY physical exam, membership records, the FDNY's Special Advisory Committee on Women, informational videos, recordings of television programs about female firefighters, and materials related to the training course at John Jay College of Criminal Justice-CUNY.
    - Center for Women in Government -- Women in Uniformed Services, 1983-1985 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Clippings, 1977-1991 (Box 5, Folder 11-25)
    - Clippings, 1992-2002 (Box 6, Folder 1-6)
    - Columbia University Survey -- "Women in the FDNY" and Report, "Gender Integration in the Fire Department of the City of New York", 1988-1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Conference -- "Women Tell the Truth", 1992 April 25 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Congress -- Committee on Education and Labor Hearings, 1991 March 5 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Constitution and By-Laws, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1988 (Box 6, Folder 11-19)
    - Correspondence, 1989-2002 (Box 7, Folder 1-15)
    - Council of the City of New York -- Committee on Women, 1986-1993 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - FDNY -- Physical Exam, Landy-Jacobs Contract, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - FDNY -- Physical Exam, Research, 1983-1984 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - FDNY -- Recruitment and Training Program, 1994-2000 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - FDNY -- Recruitment and Training Program Exam Prep Materials, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - FDNY -- Sexual Harrassment Training and Regulations, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - FDNY -- Sexual Harrassment Training and Regulations, 1986 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - FDNY -- Sexual Harrassment Training and Regulations, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - FDNY -- Special Advisory Committee on Women, 1990-1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - FDNY -- Special Advisory Committee on Women, 1993-1999 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - History, 1989-1993 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Membership, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Newsletter signed by Patricia Fitzgerald, 1983; This version is a photocopy of the handwritten original. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - New York Fire Museum Exhibit -- "Fireworks: a Celebration of FDNY Civilian and Uniformed Women, 1865-1991", 1993 May 22 - 1993 September 25 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Organizations -- Police and Fire Departments, 1982-1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Video -- "100 Years of Women" A Lifetime Television Documentary, undated; cuid35 (Box 13)
    - Video -- "A Second Look: War Opens the Door" KTVU, 2001 November 18; cuid36 (Box 12)
    - Video -- Blaze: Firecamp for Young Women, NOW Legal Defense and Education Fund, 2002 April 11; cuid37 (Box 12)
    - Video -- Channel 13 Program on Harassment, undated; cuid38 (Box 12)
    - Video -- City Council Hearing on Fire Department Recruitment, 1999 September 20; cuid39 (Box 12)
    - Video -- Donohue Segment on Sexual Harassment in the Workplace, 1992 September 10; cuid40 (Box 14)
    - Video -- FDNY Recruitment WNBC-TV, 2002 September 8; cuid41 (Box 13)
    - Video -- Female Firefighters "On the Job" (FDNY), undated; cuid102 (Box 14)
    - Video -- Female Firefighters "On the Job" (FDNY), undated (Box 12)
    - Video -- Fire Girl: The Fire Warrior -- Tokyo Fire Department, circa 2015; cuid42 (Box 12)
    - Video -- Fire Safety Education Fund NYWF Grantee, 1999; cuid43 (Box 12)
    - Video -- "Fireworks" Women's History Month Exhibit at the NYC Fire Museum, 1991 March; cuid44 (Box 12)
    - Video -- National Women's Law Center, undated; cuid45 (Box 14)
    - Video -- "Our Heroes, Ourselves" -- Lifetime Original Special, 2002 May 16; cuid46 (Box 13)
    - Video -- Parade of Classes and Celebration Ceremony, undated; cuid47 (Box 14)
    - Video -- Rocky's Promotion, 1999 June 24; cuid48 (Box 12)
    - Video -- Sex, Power and the Workplace, undated; cuid49 (Box 14)
    - Video -- Singularity presents the United States Project Firework, 2000 November 11; cuid50 (Box 14)
    - Video -- Take Our Daughters to Work PSA: "SLAM" and "Hats for Girls" -- Ms. Foundation, undated; cuid51 (Box 13, Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Video -- Take Your Daughter to Work Day, 1995 April - 2000 April; cuid52 (Box 13)
    - Video -- Take Your Daughter to Work / Walsh, 1996 (Box 12)
    - Video -- Take Your Daughter to Work -- Walsh, 2001; cuid53 (Box 12)
    - Video -- "Test of Courage: The Making of a Firefighter", undated; cuid54 (Box 12, Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Video -- "Test of Courage: The Making of a Firefighter", undated; cuid55 (Box 12)
    - Video -- Women's Candidate Training Program (FDNY), 2000 April 20; cuid56 (Box 12)
  - Subseries B: Women in Fire Suppression/Fire Service, 1983-1999
    The subseries includes correspondence, materials related to the regional and national conferences on women in firefighting sponsored by the WFS, transcriptions of interviews with Brenda Berkman from a 1987-1988 oral history project, membership, and organizational materials.
    - Articles of Incorporation, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - By-Laws, 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Clippings, 1986-1999 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Committees, 1991-1992 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Conferences -- Regional, Madison WI, 1986 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Conferences -- First National, Boulder, CO, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Conferences -- Second National, Seattle, WA, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Conferences -- Third National, Asheville, NC, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Conferences -- Fourth National, San Diego, CA, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Conferences -- Fifth National, Rockford, IL, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Conferences -- Other Organizations, 1988-1991 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence, 1983-1991 (Box 8, Folder 19-25)
    - Correspondence, 1992-1999 (Box 9, Folder 1-9)
    - Financial, 1989-1994 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - History, 1980-1991 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Membership, 1991-1993 (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Minutes -- Trustees Meetings, 1989-1995 (Box 9, Folder 13)
    - Oral History Project -- Interviews with Brenda Berkman (2) and Terese Floren, 1987-1988 (Box 9, Folder 14)
    - Policies, 1984-1991 (Box 9, Folder 15)
    - Publications -- Handbook on Women in Fire Fighting, 1992 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Survey of Women Firefighters, undated (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Trustees, 1983-1995 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- Series IV: Photographs and Memorabilia, 1980-2013; .5 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box and 1 oversize folder
  This series consists of approximately 100 black-and-white and color prints of various sizes, 19 color slides, a small amount of negatives, and one black-and-white contact sheet, with portraits, event and documentary photographs from circa 1980 to 1999. This series also includes a small amount of artifacts and memorabilia from Brenda Berkman's career as a firefighter including badges, membership cards, a UWF pin, FDNY calendars, and ephemera related to Berkman's termination in 1983.
  Photographs include a 5x7 black-and-white print and corresponding 4x5 negative of Berkman in FDNY uniform; black-and-white prints, and color prints and negatives, from a City Council Press Conference on July 19, 1992; 4x6 color prints from a Women's Action Coalition Demonstration against FDNY sexual harassment on September 10, 1992; and 8x10 black-and-white prints including Brenda Berkman speaking at a press conference with city officials, of Women Tell the Truth: A Conference on Parity, Power and Sexual Harassment on April 25th, 1992 at Hunter College, including Anita Hill and Gloria Steinem, and of Berkman and Comptroller Elizabeth Holtzman. Two large color group portraits of women firefighters include the Fourth National Conference of Fire Service Women in San Diego in 1991.
  Color slides, mostly from 1982, include images of the first women firefighters training for their physical exam in 1982, including at the Fire Academy on Randall's Island; candidate Katrina Cannon taking the oath of office in 1982 as a probationary firefighter, representing the first group; portraits of Brenda Berkman and attorney Robert King; as well as a group portrait, circa 1988, of the first women
  This series is arranged alphabetically by subject or document type.
  - Artifacts and Memorabilia [Includes Membership Cards, Badges, Pin, Ephemera], 1982-1983, undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Assorted Photographs and Memorabilia, 1983-2001 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Berkman, Brenda -- Photographs, 1987, 1993, undated (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Booklet -- "The Role of Women in the Fire Service," FEMA, 1980 August (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1990, 1993 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a Letter from Brenda Berkman identifying some individuals in photographs.
  - Calendars -- UFA FDNY and UFO ASSN, 1983-1985 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - City Council Press Conference Photographs, 1992 July 19 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Ephemera, 2018-2022 (Box Shared Tamiment 165, Folder 10)
  - Group Photographs of Female Firefighters, 2006, undated (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Group Portraits of Women Firefighters, 1991, undated (Box Shared Tamiment XOS002)
    Includes a photo of the Fourth National Conference of Fire Service Women in San Diego.
  - Little Tradeswomen Coloring Book, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 15, Folder 14)
  - Portrait of Brenda Berkman -- First Woman Firefighter of New York City, undated; 4x5 Negative (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Poster -- "The Bravest Women of Brooklyn" FDNY, circa 2000s (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS007, Folder 3)
  - Poster -- Brenda Berkman at Education for Justice Keynote Address, circa 2011-2012 (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS007, Folder 3)
  - Poster -- Brenda Berkman at JWT Differenter Women's Heritage Month Speakers Series, 2013 (Flat-file-folder 2)
  - Poster -- Group Photo of Women in the FDNY, circa 2000s (Flat-file-folder 2)
  - Poster -- National Organization for Women and Brenda Berkman, undated (Flat-file-folder 1)
  - Poster -- Sports Illustrated Article on Women 9/11 First Responders, 2001 (Flat-file-folder 2)
  - Slides, circa 1980-1989 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    Includes group portraits and photographs of the first women firefighters of New York City.
  - United Women Firefighters -- Assorted Photos, "Women Tell the Truth," and Others, 1992 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - United Women Firefighters -- Various Color Photos, 1999, undated (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Women's Action Coalition Demonstration Photographs, 1992 September 10 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - 2019 Accretion: Organizational Documents and Photographs, 1982-2015 (Box 17, Folder 3-5)